here is the city of Bakhmut 70,000 inhabitants there were
вот город бахмут 70.000 жителей было
now zero It’s just that it was destroyed and no one
сейчас ноль Просто он уничтожен и никто
lives there I will also deny it I don’t
там не живёт я бу так же отпираться я не
I keep my opinion Well, I shouldn’t
я держу свои мнение Ну я не должен его
express it at work or anywhere else so
высказывать на работе или где-либо ещё
as not to expose myself, I’m a
дабы не подставляться я же
sane
здравомыслящий
person, but I  from the city of Khmelnitsky
человек доб ут Я из города Хмельницкий
Where are you from St. Petersburg and who are you
Вы откуда с Питера на кого
studying to be? I’ve already graduated as a primary
учитесь я уже отучился учитель начальных
school teacher. It’s cool.
классов прикольно
What are you talking about here, a primary
О чём общаетесь тут учитель начальных
school teacher? So far, we’ve just stopped by about anything.
классов Пока ни о чём только
It’s cool, yeah, if you’re interested. If you’re a
угу вот если вас вот интересно Если вы
primary school teacher, a
учитель младших классов подойдёт к вам
child in the lower grade comes up to you and says  uh, what’s
ребёнок в младшем классе говорит э как
your name by the way, Grigory Grigory
вас зовут кстати Григорий Григорий
says teacher Grigory
говорит учитель Григорий Скажите
Please tell me why Russia attacked
пожалуйста а почему Россия напала на
Ukraine how do you explain it to a child
Украину как ты объяснишь вот ребёнку
like this I’ll have to tell him
так я должен буду сказать ему о том
that the sun is a military special military
что солнышко это воен специальна военная
operation special operation if
операция специально операция вот если у
you have any questions for you
тебя есть какие-то вопросы тебе могут
parents can tell them Parents can’t
рассказать них родители Родители не
quite answer this question and
совсем могу ответить на этот вопрос и
so on is beyond my competence I
так далее вне моей компетенции Я же не
can’t have dialogues with children on
могу с детьми вести диалоги на
political topics it was
политические темы было
wrong it’s dechany la che la
неправильно это дечаны ла че ла
Well about s you told him yes What is it s
Ну про с ты ему сказал да Что это с
understood What if the child  will come and ask
понял А если ребёнок придёт и спрашивает
why Hitler attacked
А почему Гитлер напал на
Poland, this is the same
Польшу это та же самая
policy, again a question for parents,
политика опять же вопрос к родителям
stop, stop, that is, it turns out that children can be
стоп стоп То есть получается детей можно
taken to some events on May 9,
водить на 9 мая
this is not politics, but to say
мероприятия это не политика а сказать
why the war started, this is politics, yes,
почему началась война это политика да
I will say, I will  I’ll have to say Wow,
я я скажу я я должен буду сказать Ух ты
wow, you’re a great guy for being so
Вот это да ты большой молодец что таким
interested in this, we’ll
интересуешься об этом мы с тобой
talk about this in the sixth or seventh grade,
поговорим в шестом или в седьмом классе
but if you’re very interested in this, you
но если тебе это очень интересно ты
can prepare a report on this
можешь приготовить доклад на эту
topic, it’s cool, you have a good idea,
тему прикольно хорошо представляешь
the kid comes with a report Yes, on the Internet
малыш приходит с докладом Да в интернете
and he says that, for example, in class they
и он говорит что например на уроке там
go to the blackboard and say Report Yes,
выходят к доске и говорит Докладываю Да
uh, Russia attacked Ukraine because
ээ Россия напала на Украину потому что у
we have a crazy president, in short,
нас сумасшедший президент короче
Vladimir Putin decided to take over his
Владимир Путин решил захватить е себе
neighboring
соседнюю
country, your actions, I’ll say Wow,
страну твои действия я скажу Ух ты А
why did you decide that or she decided to me
почему ты так решил или решила она мне
will answer or will he answer me yes and he
ответит или он мне ответит да а он а он
will answer like because Russia
ответит типа потому что Россия
destroyed Mariupol
уничтожила Мариуполь
Bakhmut is beating Kharkov
бахмут бьёт Харьков
Kiev I shouldn’t lead my children into
Киев Я не должен вести детьми
political dilemmas of some kind so
политические какие-то дилеммы поэтому
I can’t comment on this from the point of
я не могу такое комментировать с точки
view I will need to talk to
зрения Мне нужно будет разговаривать с
their
их
parents most likely A  why
родителями скорее всего А зачем с
talk to your parents if the child is just
родителями говорить если ребёнок просто
asking something about the world? And you and your
спрашивает что-то о мире А вы с
parents, why are you talking to your parents?
родителями зачем с родителями неплохую
You bent a good line, it’s interesting. You, for
вы загнули линию интересно Вы же
example, if he asks those That’s
например он же если он спрашивает те Вот
why the Earth revolves around the Sun, so
почему Земля крутится вокруг Солнца так
I call the parents like, well,
вызываю родителей типа ну что
so yours are different  questions for a second I’ll also do something like this
Так у тебя разные вопросы секунду я тоже
somehow, let’s do it So,
тогда вот так вот как-то сделаю что
damn you, you’re sitting and
А вы блин вы вы получается сидите и вот
having dialogues on this topic, you’re
ведёте диалоги на эту тему вас наше
interested in our opinion, I just look, the idea is
мнение интересует я просто смотри идея в
that I’m also a teacher, I’m also a teacher,
том что я тоже учитель Я тоже учитель У
I have a pedagogical  education Yes,
меня есть педагогическое образование Да
I have 18 years of practice, in 2 years
у меня 18 лет практики через 2 года
it will be my twentieth, he said that the
будет двадцатого сказал что учитель
primary school teacher told me I’m just a teacher. I
младших классов мне просто я учитель У
have two, me and a primary
меня есть два я и учитель младших
school teacher and a history teacher.
классов и учитель истории
That is, I, but now I teach
Вот то есть я но сейчас преподаю именно
history, now I don’t teach in primary school,
историю сейчас в младших классах не
but I  taught in elementary
преподаю но я преподавал в младших
grades you allow yourself to express your personal opinion
классах вы позволяете себе личное мнение
on of course and why of course
высказывать на конечно а заче конечно
yeah well why look if for example
ага ну а почему смотри если например
a child asks me Yes for example
меня спрашивает ребёнок Да например
Why Ukraine separated from the USSR and
Почему Украина отделилась от СССР и
gained independence
получила независимость
so should I answer her or I will say this
так я должен ей ответить или я скажу это
concerns the past what has already happened but
касается прошедшего что уже произошло но
when it’s good in a given place Yes, if a child
когда в данный мот хорошо Да если ребнок
asks me Yes, why did Russia
меня спрашивает Да а почему Россия
attack us? I also answer yes. Well, well,
напала на нас Я тоже отвечаю да Ну а
there we are, as if we were not
там мы же как бы мы же не на территорию
attacking the territory of Ukraine, rather, but rather NATO,
Украины нападаем скорее а на НАТО
which was doing various things. Well, yes,
которая делала различные действия Ну да
yes, come on.  Tell me tell me
да давай давай Расскажи расскажи вот мне
let’s imagine that I’m a child Yes tell
давай представь что я ребнок Да расскажи
me which NATO you bombed in Kharkov
мне какое НАТО вы разбомбили в Харькове
in Kiev You can talk about this
в Киеве Вот вы ули могу говорить об этом
with a child that’s good Yes let’s do that let’s
с ребнком это хоро Да давай так давай
do that child Yes I complained
так давайте так ребёнок Да пожаловался
that you don’t want to talk to him and I  Dad
что вы не хотите с ним говорить и я папа
I came to you and I want to ask you
Его я пришёл к вам и хочу у вас спросить
yes Tell me please
да Скажите пожалуйста
Grigory What NATO is our country Bombed
Григорий Какое НАТО наша страна Бомбила
in Bakhmut, here is the city of Bakhmut 70,000
в бахмуте вот город бахмут 70.000
inhabitants were now zero It’s just that it was
жителей было сейчас ноль Просто он
destroyed No one lives there I will also
уничтожен Никто там жит я буду также
deny I don’t I keep my opinions Well I
отпираться я не я держу свои мнения Ну я
shouldn’t  express it at work or
не должен его высказывать на работе или
anywhere else so as not to expose yourself, I’m a
где-либо ещё дабы не подставляться я же
sane person. Why do I need to expose myself somewhere?
здравомыслящий человек Зачем мне где-то
In the sense of exposing yourself And to you What
вот В смысле подставляться А вам Что
is forbidden to you? Talk about politics, it’s the
запрещено вас Говорите о политике это
same as me telling a child about something I do
всё равно что я скажу ребёнку о том что
n’t know. You know, a five-year-old child.
не знаю Ты знаешь ребёнок пятилетний яму
You know that after death there is nothing Yes,
Ты знаешь что после смерти нет ничего Да
now with Burn all the water I have such a
сейчас с Горите все воду у меня такая
Faith, I’m telling it to you, and their
Вера я её вам рассказываю а у них в
family has Islam. Yes, even in Ukraine there may be
семье Ислам Да даже в Украине могут быть
families that don’t do well. Well, come on,
семьи которые дется не Хорошо давай
look, come on, let’s play this way, for
смотри давай давай давай таким образом
example, I uh  also your
поиграем так например я ээ тоже твой
colleague your colleague we are in Uchita We are
коллега твой коллега мы мы в Учите Мы в
sitting in the teachers' room, in short, we
учительской сидим короче там в шахматы
play chess, we communicate like this Yes, and I, in short,
играем так общаемся Да вот и я короче
started the topic Listen, what do you think, what do you think
вот завёл тему Слушай а как ты считаешь
we attacked Ukraine, what will you
а что мы напали на Украину что ты
answer me as your colleague
ответишь мне как своему коллеге
honestly, I really  in
честно я на самом
fact, in fact, I’m against war
деле на самом деле против войны в любом
in any form, I don’t support
в любой форме я вообще не поддерживаю то
what’s happening on either side at all.
что происходит ни с той ни с той стороны
I’m for people to come to an agreement. No,
Я за то чтобы люди договаривались Не а
what’s going on with that one hundred, look,
что происходит с той сто не что смотри
Russia attacked Ukraine from this side,
Россия на Украину напала с этой стороны
everything’s clear  And on the other hand, that Ukraine
всё понятно А с той стороны что Украина
attacked Russia or
на Россию напала или
that come on, you don’t Yes, come on, you don’t cut it
что давай ты не Да у Давай ты не среза
Yes, look, I’m with you in the smoking room Yes,
Да вот смотри я я с тобой в курилке Да
this is Teacher’s I’m a
вот это Учительской Я учитель
physical education teacher Yes, you’re a junior class And I’m a
физкультуры Да ты младший класс А я
physical education teacher, I’m a simple guy, I can drag a
Физрук я простой парень я могу втащить
scoreboard  If you don’t like something, yes, I
табло Если что-то не нравится да я
say Listen, explain, you’re smart You’ve
говорю Слушай объясни вот ты умный Ты
finished This is what you tell the children, you
заканчивал Вот это детям рассказываешь
teach that we attacked Ukraine Explain
учишь что мы напали на Украину Объясни
to me I’m generally incompetent in this, I do
мне Я вообще в этом некомпетентен я
n’t get involved in politics at all Do you think I
вообще не лезу в политику Как ты думаешь
know what I don’t like This is the situation for me  I do
знаю что мне не нравится Э ситуация мне
n’t like it when civilians suffer
не нравится чтобы страдали гражданские
because the guys on top
люди из того что дяденьки сверху там
decide something among themselves. I’m
что-то между собой решают Мне это вообще
not interested in that at all. Which guys decide?
не интерес не А какие дяденьки решают
Which guys decide among
Какие дяденьки решают между
themselves? Well, how is territory divided or
собо Ну как делится территории или
something else happens? How do you? How do
что-то ещё такое происходит Как ты Как
you do it?  guys, not guys, what do you
ты давай так дяденьки не дяденьки вот ты
think, yes, uh, how should
как считаешь да ээ чем должна
this war end, how do you see the world,
закончиться эта война как ты видишь мир
the end of the war I believe that I believe
окончание войны Я считаю что я считаю
that any life is valuable, it cannot be
что любая жизнь ценна её нельзя
rendered empty if, let’s say, in
переводить в пустую если допустим в
forty-five there, yes, the Great Patriotic
сорок пятом там да Великая Отечественная
War, it was clear why people were there
война было понятно за что там люди
they are fighting on both sides, by the way, it was
борются с обеих сторон кстати было
Pony from the Ukrainian side from the Ukrainian
Поня с украинской стороны с украинской
side It’s clear We are fighting for our
стороны Понятно Мы боремся за свою
freedom Russia attacked us How the Germans
свободу Россия на нас напала Как немцы
attacked In 1941,
напали В сорок первом на Советский Союз
everything is clear on the Soviet Union and what are you fighting for, what did you
всё чётко а за что вы боретесь за что вы
come to kill for,
пришли убивать
let’s look again  since you
давайте давай ещ раз смотри ещ раз Вы
attacked Ukraine or Ukraine is attacking
напали на Украину или Украина на
you no it’s not the same from which side the
вас нет не так с какой стороны начались
fighting began wed so
боевые действия сре так
on What a
на Какая
wound Come on so
рана Вот давай так
what’s your
какая сво
howl
вой с
with Germany everything Germany is the aggressor everything
с Германия всё Германия агрессор всё
is clear now here which country sent its
чётко теперь тут какая страна ввела свои
troops Russia to Ukraine or Ukraine to
войска Россия в Украину или Украина в
Russia, Russia, who is the aggressor, but however,
Россию Россия кто агрессор но однако у
you fought once again, once again,
вас же вели бовы ещё раз ещё раз ещё раз
once again, who led his troops to another
ещё раз кто вёл свои войска в другую
country, Russia Wait, Who led us,
страну Россия Подожди Кто вёл у нас ещё
once again, we have already heard you, I understand, it
раз мы вас уже услышали я понимаю вам
will probably become easier for you,
наверняка станет легче
you say now, let’s
вы говорите тепер давай лет
do it for years  you have
получается у вас
various military operations taking place on
происходит различные боевые действия на
your territory your yours are not so this is
территории ваше вашей ваше не не так это
because Russia attacked Well, don’t
из-за того что Россия напала Ну не
wait again, look again, we have
подожди ещё раз смотри ещё раз у нас
no military operations because of this Because
никаких боевых действий этого изза Чего
of what, a special military operation is
изза чего специальная военная операция
not stop like What’s it got to do with it  military
обя не стоп как При чём тут военная
operation I'm talking about the fourteenth year,
операция я тебе про четырнадцатый год не
Russia didn't attack in the second year Russia
Россия же напала не в ть втором Россия в
attacked in what
чем напала
You probably didn't understand once again sst me you did
Ты наверное не понял ещё раз сст меня ты
n't understand probably what kind of Russia
не понял наверное какой сво Россия
attacked in the damn year on the night of
напала в чертом году в ночь с 26 на 27
February 26-27 of the fourteenth year Russia
февраля четырнадцатого года Россия
began the occupation  Crimea since April 12 of which
начала оккупацию Крыма с 12 апреля чего
year the occupation of Donetsk Lugansk Yes, well, before
года оккупацию Донецка Луганска Да ну до
that there were no military actions.
этого Никаких действий не было боевых У
We have here in your country
нас тут у вас на территории страны
various military actions taking place
происходят различные боевые действия
between you. Who is there where they bombed
между вами Кто там к там где там бомбили
in Donets, so that’s it again, look, look,
в Донец так это ж ещё раз смотри смотри
I’m I  No, I’m like a physical education teacher like
я я Нет я как учитель физкультуры как у
ours, listen to how we have your position, I
нас слушайте как вот у нас ваша позиция
mean, this is what’s happening here, you’re there,
яс у нас так происходит у вас там
you’re here, and
находится вы здесь происходит и для того
there’s a risk that this
чтобы происходит риск того что это
will start on our border or
начнётся на границе у нас или уже
will already start on our territory in order
начнётся на нашей территории для того
to  this didn’t happen,
чтобы этого не было
the operation started so that this is before now I’ll
началась операция чтобы это предо теперь
explain, look,
объясняю смотри
I’m not telling you how it’s presented to you. I’m
Я не говорю как тебе преподносится Я же
telling you, you have your own bowler hat on your head,
говорю у тебя есть сво котелок на голове
look, there are no military operations. We didn’t have any military operations
смотри никаких боевых действий У нас не
here in Ukraine, and before yours, we had
было тут в Украине да до вашего сво у
Russia in 1414.  Ukraine
нас в 14м году Россия напала на Украину
was captured by Crimea and part of the Donetsk and
захватила Крым и часть Донецкой и
Lugansk regions and the war with Russia has been going on
Луганской области и война с России идёт
since 1914. Why have
с четырнадцатого года не с ть второго С
we already been at war for 10 years?
чего 10 лет у нас уже идёт Война 10 лет
Russia has been bombing Ukraine for 10 years, so that’s
Россия бомбит Украину 10 лет так вот
why you attacked why you attacked us in
зачем вы напали зачем вы напали на нас в
1414  having captured Crimea Donetsk
четырнадцатом году захватив Крым Донецк
Lugansk you are asking me me Swa
Луганск вы это спрашиваете меня меня Сва
Yes why Okay The earth is flat and Hitler
Да зачем О'кей Земля плоская а Гитлер
was a pagan there is an information war going on You
был язычником происходит информационная
see I don’t care at all
война Понимаете мне вообще по барабану У
You have your own position we have some kind of
вас своя позиция у нас какая-то там
maybe our own But we are just here Find
возможно своя Но мы просто здесь Находи
Now wait for this  you want to hear from us now
Вот подожди вот что вы сейчас от нас
Look, I want to see Well,
хотите услышать Смотри я хочу вот Ну
look, we decided with you, but who is
смотри мы ж решили с тобой да что кто
to blame Russia because you attacked, you
виноват Россия потому что напала ты
started that we had military operations, we
начал что у нас были боевые действия мы
sorted it out with you that we didn’t have it,
разобрались с тобой что у нас не было
Russia is good at solving the question, let’s do this
Россия хорошо вопрос реша во давай так
who is to blame who
кто виноват кто
Give you a question who is to blame for this
Давай вам вопрос кто виноват в этой
war I asked the question
войне я вопрос задал
which pasta Monster is to blame for what What do
какой макаронный Монстр винова что Что
you want from us terms
вы хотите от нас
I want to hear what you think
услы Я хочу услышать как Вы считаете Вот
You are ordinary citizens What do you think who is
вы простые граждане Как вы считаете кто
to blame for what started This I believe that
виноват что началось Это я считаю что
any life All of you  you have already said everything
любая жизнь Всё вы уже всё сказали то
that you wanted from us you are now starting
что вы хотели от нас вы сейчас начинаете
Rask yes those I don’t like
Раск да те Я не люблю
any wait you
никакие подожди вот вы
heard shut up you heard from us
услышали помолчи вы услышали От нас то
what you want we answered you and that’s
что вы хотите мы вам это ответили и вот
why you are promoting this topic Please
зачем вы раскручивается эту тему Вот
tell me you somehow  you want
скажите пожалуйста вы как-то хотите нас
to hook us,
зацепить
provoke us, first of all, don’t interrupt, don’t
спровоцировать вопервых не перебивай не
interrupt me when I interrupt, look,
перебивай меня когда перебиваю я смотри
I’m communicating with ordinary people, I don’t have
я общаюсь с простыми людьми Я же не
a claim on you, [ __ ], I’m not saying
претензию к вам гою Я не говорю
that I’m the elder, I’m still the elder, let’s
что я старший Я всё-таки старший Давай
have respect, look, I’m not saying that you do
имею уважение Смотри я не говорю что вы
n’t give me the right  interrupt
не даёт м право перебивать
me interrupt nya I’m not saying that you are
меня перебивай ня Я не говорю что вы
bad, I’m like ordinary people, I want to
плохие я у вас как у простых людей хочу
understand how you
понять как вы
think, we said any life is a price
мыслите мы сказали любая жизнь цена
conflict conflict War is war This is war, it’s
конфликт конфликт Война войной Это война
not victory, it’s not defeat, it’s not the
это не победа не поражение это не
attacker, it’s not the loser This is war in
напавший не Проигравший Это война в
any of its manifestations war  this is what this is
любом своём проявлении война это что это
death There is no good war there is no bad
смерть Нет хорошей войны нет плохой
war war is war it is useless to think about this
войны война - это война мыслить об этом
we are not politicians we are not leading
бесполезно мы не политики мы не руководи
this war we have nothing to do with this
этой войной мы никак к этому не касаемся
we can be called up for this war we
мы можем быть призваны на Эту войну мы
can die for this in ours they
можем погибнуть на это во наши
can take you  for this war you
могут е вас возьмут на эту войну вы
will kill people in Ukraine
будете убивать людей в Украине
so they will give the order
так приказ дадут
Yes, just like you Look on the one hand on the
Да также как вы Смотри с одной стороны с
one hand you say that we are not
одной стороны вы говорите что мы не
interested, they are all there and on the other
интересуемся это там они всё да с другой
hand you will just kill
стороны вы будете просто убивать
some people, innocent people in a foreign
каких-то людей невинных людей в чужой
country  my goal is to protect my
стране моя цель защитить свою
family alive and healthy at least partially
семью живым и здоровым хотя бы частично
partially here look look
частично вот смотри смотри
Yes I I I think so let's
Да я я я думаю так давай
cut
так подрез
uh you firstly secondly
ээ вы во-первых во-вторых
Yes I think that if you were
Да я думаю что если бы вы были
cha If you were partially whole Yes it
ча Если бы вы были частично целые Да это
was  it would be cool yes People like you are forming the
было бы круто да Такие как вы формируют
New Nazi generation in the Russian
Новое нацистское поколение в Российской
Federation Yes you are
Федерации Да ты вот
this teacher yes you are responsible for those
этот учитель да ты ответствен за тех
who grow up you are given orders Yes and you
кого вырастают вам дают приказы Да и вы
carry them out you make slaves of the
их выполняете вы делаете из детей рабов
system who hang Zaki Yes they go and
системы которые вешают Заки Да ходят и
say that there are Ukrainians in short  And so
говорят что там короче украинцы И так
on Yes, everyone attacked. So just
дальше Да напали всё Поэтому просто
go. Yes, just
идёте Да вот
like that, this is a
так вот так
new channel. Write to the new channel right away.
це новый канал Пиши на нього прямо зараз
Put the dialer to cancel your SPO.
Постав дзвоник щоб отримати ус СПО
We’ll be on
вчення будем на
call L
зв'язку L